Register of the Archives of the Soviet communist party and Soviet state microfilm collection: Russian State Archive of Contemporary History (Rossiiskii gosudarstvennyi arkhiv noveishei istorii - RGANI)
Hoover Institution Archives
- Fond 89, Communist Party of the Soviet Union on Trial records, 1919-1992; 24 reels (Reel 1.989-1.1012)
  - Opis 18
    - Cover letter to G. Malenkov from S. Kruglov, I. Serov, and A. Paniushkin accompanying documents on establishing the 12th Special Department of the Main Intelligence Directorate of the USSR MVD (Ministry of Internal Affairs); draft resolution of the TsK KPSS, with handwritten amendments; brief statement re location of the documents, 1953 September (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 30)
    - Two identical cover letters to G. Malenkov from S. Kruglov, I. Serov, and A. Paniushkin accompanying documents on establishing 12th Special Department under the Main Intelligence Directorate of the USSR MVD (Ministry of Internal Affairs); statute and structure and staff charts of the 12th Department, 1953 September-November (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 31)
    - File is unavailable, 1918-1992 (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 32)
    - Memorandum to N. Khrushchev from S. Kruglov and R. Rudenko re reviewing files of those convicted by the Special Board (Osoboe soveshchanie) under NKVD (includes number of people convicted annually, 1934-1953); resolution of the TsK KPSS, 1953 December (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 33)
    - File is unavailable, 1918-1992 (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 34)
    - Report to N. Bulganin, Chairman of the USSR Council of Ministers, from I. Serov, Chairman of the KGB, re complaints from people inquiring about the fate of family members sentenced to death by the Special Board (Osoboe soveshchanie or troĭka OGPU-NKVD), 1956 April (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 35)
    - Memorandum to L. Brezhnev from I. Serov, Chairman of the KGB, re reorganization of correctional labor institutions of the Ministry of Internal Affairs (MVD), 1956 May (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 36)
    - Report to the TsK KPSS from I. Serov, Chairman of the KGB, re anti-Soviet incidents and disturbances registered on the day of elections to the local Soviets of the People's Deputies and on the day before elections, 1957 March (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 37)
    - Memorandum to R. Rudenko, USSR Prosecutor General, from I. Serov, Chairman of the KGB, stating the refusal of the KGB to reconsider criminal cases initiated before 1935, 1957 April (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 38)
    - File is unavailable, 1918-1992 (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 39)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from R. Rudenko, USSR Prosecutor General, and I. Serov, Chairman of the KGB, requesting TsK KPSS approval of the rehabilitation of V. Sharangovich, former First Secretary of the Central Committee of the Communist Party (Bolsheviks) of Belorussia, sentenced to death after the trial of the block of anti-Soviet rights and Trotskyites together with N. Bukharin and A. Rykov, 1957 December (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 40)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from R. Rudenko, USSR Prosecutor General, and I. Serov, Chairman of the KGB, re rehabilitation of T. Deribas, former Chief of the NKVD of Dalnevostochnyi (Far East) krai, sentenced to death by the Military Board of the USSR Supreme Soviet for counterrevolutionary activity in 1938, 1957 December (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 41)
    - Summary of the Committee for State Security (KGB) file on Academician L. Landau, with cover letter to TsK KPSS (to comrade V. Kirillin personally) from I. Serov, Chairman of the KGB, 1957 December (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 42)
    - File is unavailable, 1918-1992 (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 43)
    - Cover letter to N. Shchelokov, Minister of Public Order, from IU. Andropov, Chairman of the KGB, re the Statute on the Committee for State Security (KGB) of the USSR Council of Ministers (not included), 1968 May (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 44)
    - Draft resolution of the TsK KPSS re resumption of emigration of Soviet citizens to Israel; memorandum to the TsK KPSS from IU. Andropov and A. Gromyko, 1968 June (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 45)
    - File is unavailable, 1918-1992 (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 46)
    - Extract from the minutes of the TsK KPSS Politburo re revocation of citizenship of I. Gabai and A. Marchenko; two draft resolutions of the Presidium of the USSR Supreme Soviet, 1968 April (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 47)
    - Summary of the coded telegram from the Ukrainian KGB re results of the elections to the Supreme Soviet of the Ukraine and to the local Soviets, and re anti-Soviet inscriptions on ballots, 1971 June (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 48)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from IU. Andropov, Chairman of the KGB, re a request of the writer A. Perventsev to trace the persons constantly threatening him by phone, 1972 July (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 49)
    - File is unavailable, 1918-1992 (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 50)
    - Personal cover letter to V. (Galkin?) accompanying proposals of the Committee for State Security regarding requirements for the format of the documents directed from the Committee for State Security (KGB) to the TsK KPSS; list of documents attached to the cover letter; memorandum with the KGB proposals; contents of the said documents, 1973 June (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 51)
    - Personal letter to P. Laptev from V. Galkin and N. Novikov re documents from the Committee for State Security (see file 51); memorandum with proposals of the Committee for State Security (KGB), edited and amended, 1974 May (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 52)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from IU. Andropov, Chairman of the Committee for State Security, re awarding the sculptor E. Neizvestnyi a state contract to prevent his emigration, 1974 October (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 53)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS (personally to K. Chernenko) from IU. Andropov, Chairman of the Committee for State Security, proposing to deny IE. Bonner's (Academician Sakharov's wife) request to go abroad for treatment, 1975 February (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 54)
    - Files are unavailable, 1918-1992 (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 55-57)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from the Committee for State Security (KGB) requesting approval of the trip of Soviet witnesses at the trial of a Nazi criminal in the city of Halle (East Germany), 1975 June (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 58)
    - File is unavailable, 1918-1992 (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 59)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from IU. Andropov, Chairman of the Committee for State Security, re publication in the press of the decree of the Presidium of the USSR Supreme Soviet depriving the writer V. Maksimov of Soviet citizenship, 1975 October (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 60)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from IU. Andropov, Chairman of the Committee for State Security, re objections to the reunion of the traitor V. Agapov with his family, 1975 October (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 61)
    - File is unavailable, 1918-1992 (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 62)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from IU. Andropov, Chairman of the Committee for State Security, re stopping foreign enemies' financial support of people in the Soviet Union hostile to the Soviet regime, 1977 March (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 63)
    - File is unavailable, 1918-1992 (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 64)
    - File is unavailable, 1918-1992 (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 65)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Kuznetsov and S. Tsvigun re grant of a permission to hunt in the Soviet Union to the Iranian Shah's brother, Prince Abdor-Reza Pahlavi; draft resolution of the TsK KPSS; draft instruction to the Soviet ambassador to Iran; statement of the Prince's personal data, 1977 May (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 66)
    - File is unavailable, 1918-1992 (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 67)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from IU. Andropov, Chairman of the Committee for State Security, re disapproval of the amendment to Article 54 of the draft USSR Constitution banning detention of citizens without legal grounds, 1977 September (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 68)
    - Files are unavailable, 1918-1992 (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 69-71)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from N. Shchelokov and V. Chebrikov re transfer of especially dangerous criminals from Vladimirskaia prison #2 to other MVD institutions, 1978 March (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 72)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from IU. Andropov, Chairman of the Committee for State Security, re inquiries about "independent trade unions" in the USSR, 1978 April (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 73)
    - Files are unavailable, 1918-1992 (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 74-79)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from IU. Andropov, Chairman of the Committee for State Security, re detention of A. Amin, former Chief of Counterintelligence of Afghanistan [and nephew of H. Amin], V. Zirak, bodyguard of the former President, and Z. Omar, physician (in response to the personal request of Afghan President B. Karmal); brief note stating that the memorandum has been presented to the TsK KPSS leadership, 1979 December - 1980 January (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 80)
    - Files are unavailable, 1918-1992 (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 81-83)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Chebrikov, Chairman of the Committee for State Security, re draft regulations for agents and confidential persons of the Committee for State Security (KGB), with brief notes confirming approval of the Regulations by the TsK KPSS, 1983 June-August (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 84)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Chebrikov, Chairman of the Committee for State Security, re regulations for contacts of Soviet officials with foreigners aimed to prevent government officials from accepting bribes; draft resolution of the TsK KPSS; draft resolution of the USSR Council of Ministers, 1986 January (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 85)
    - File is unavailable, 1918-1992 (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 86)
    - Report on the situation in educational institutions of the Committee for State Security (KGB); cover letter to V. Chebrikov, Chairman of the KGB, from N. Savinkin, Chief of the Department of Administrative Organs, 1985 January (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 87)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Chebrikov, Chairman of the KGB, summarizing results of selecting Party, Soviet, and VLKSM (All-Union Young Communists League) members for education at the Higher School of the KGB, 1985 September (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 88)
    - File is unavailable, 1918-1992 (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 89)
    - File is unavailable, 1918-1992 (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 90)
    - Memorandum to the central committees of communist parties of the Soviet republics and KPSS committees in krais and oblasts (kraikoms and obkoms) re rules for establishing ciphered connection among KPSS committees in case of imposition of martial law; cover letter to N. Yemokhonov, Deputy Chairman of the KGB, from V. Butin, Deputy Chief of the General Department, 1985 November (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 91)
    - Statement on measures taken by the Committee for State Security (KGB) re the TsK KPSS Politburo decision of November 29, 1985, in response to M. Gorbachev's memorandum banning misrepresentation of facts and data in reports to the TsK KPSS and other leading bodies of the country, 1985 December (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 92)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from E. Shevardnadze and V. Chebrikov, re granting authorization to the family of the terminally ill film director A. Tarkovskii to visit him in Paris, 1986 January (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 93)
    - Memorandum to the Department of the Administrative Organs of the TsK KPSS from V. Chebrikov, Chairman of the Committee for State Security (KGB), with a report on measures taken by the KGB to improve training and to raise qualifications of the KGB cadres, 1986 January (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 94)
    - Report to the TsK KPSS from V. Chebrikov and G. Marchuk re fulfillment of the resolution of the TsK KPSS On Measures Regulating Scientific, Engineering, Economic, and Other Relations with Foreign Organizations, Institutions, and Companies on the Territory of the USSR, 1986 January (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 95)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Chebrikov, Chairman of the KGB, re selection of Party, Soviet, and VLKSM (All- Union Young Communists League) members to work with the Committee for State Security (KGB); draft distribution list for selection of Party, Soviet, and VLKSM members from Soviet republics, autonomous republics, krais, and oblasts to work with the KGB; draft resolution of the TsK KPSS, 1986 April (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 96)
    - Memorandum to M Gorbachev from V. Chebrikov, Chairman of the KGB, re an anonymous letter reporting the priest Bobkov's abuse of his position, and measures scheduled to strengthen control over congregations' financial and economic activities; brief note of V. Chebrikov approving the measures listed in the memorandum, 1986 February (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 97)
    - Statute of the International Department of the TsK KPSS, approved by M Gorbachev; brief notes, 1986 May (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 98)
    - Letter to N. Kruchina, Administrator of the Administration of TsK KPSS Affairs, from M. Yermakov, Deputy Chairman of the Committee of State Security (KGB), requesting that samples of the identification cards of TsK members, candidate members, members of the KPSS Central Control Commission, and of executive officials of the TsK KPSS be sent to the Committee for State Security (KGB) to arrange for visits of such officials to the KGB, 1986 June (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 99)
    - File is unavailable, 1918-1992 (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 100)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Chebrikov, S. L. Sokolov, and V. A. Shamshin re development of a photoelectric system for transmitting Pravda (Truth) newspaper to independent printing stations, 1986 July (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 101)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Chebrikov, Chairman of the KGB, re counteractions against anti-Soviet campaigns on human rights; draft resolution of the TsK KPSS, 1986 July (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 102)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from E. Shevardnadze, V. Chebrikov, A. N. Yakovlev, and V. Zagladin re appeal of A. King, President of the Club of Rome, inviting more Soviet representatives to join the Club; draft resolution of the TsK KPSS, 1986 August (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 103)
    - File is unavailable, 1918-1992 (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 104)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from IE. Ligachev and V. Chebrikov re terminating the jamming of broadcasts of Voice of America, BBC, Peking Radio, and Radio Korea, 1986 September (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 105)
    - File is unavailable, 1918-1992 (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 106)
    - Memorandum to M. Gorbachev from V. Chebrikov, A. Rekunkov, and N. Savinkin re review of the criminal case of Professors of the Agricultural Academy A. Chaianov, N. Kondratiev, N. Makarov, and A. Chelintsev, charged with counterrevolutionary activity in 1932, 1986 October (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 107)
    - Chebrikov, Chairman of the KGB, re awarding E. Mielke, Minister of State Security of the German Democratic Republic, the Hero of the Soviet Union title; draft resolution of the TsK KPSS; decree of the Presidium of the USSR Supreme Soviet, 1987 November (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 108)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from L. Zaikov, V. Chebrikov, E. Shevardnadze, S. L. Sokolov, A. Dobrynin, IU. Masliukov, and L. Riabev re a statement of the Soviet government on renewal of testing of nuclear weapons; draft resolution of the TsK KPSS; draft instructions to the Soviet ambassadors to the German Democratic Republic, Hungary, Romania, Poland, Laos, Cuba, Cambodia, Czechoslovakia, North Korea, Bulgaria, Mongolia, and North Vietnam; draft instructions to the Soviet ambassadors to Greece, Argentina, Tanzania, India, Mexico, Sweden, and Zimbabwe, and to the Soviet representatives to the United Nations and the International Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA); draft instructions to the Soviet ambassadors to the United States, Great Britain, France, and China, 1986 December (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 109)
    - File is unavailable, 1918-1992 (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 110)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Chebrikov, A. Rekunkov, V. Terebilov, and B. Kravtsov re releasing from punishment and criminal liability persons charged with anti-Soviet propaganda and distribution of fabrications discrediting the Soviet state and its social system; draft resolution of the TsK KPSS, 1986 December (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 111)
    - Memorandum to M. Gorbachev from V. Chebrikov and A. Rekunkov re administering Articles 70, 190', and 142 of the Criminal Code of the RSFSR and corresponding articles of criminal codes of other republics (re anti-Soviet propaganda and distribution of fabrications discrediting the Soviet state and its social system), and re measures to improve administering the articles, 1987 February (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 112)
    - Memorandum to IU. Zuev, Deputy Chief of the International Department, from F. Bobkov, Deputy Chairman of the KGB, re response to an inquiry of French correspondents in Moscow about human rights activists A. Marchenko and A. Ogorodnikov, 1987 February (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 113)
    - Extracts from a memorandum of the conversation of Academician A. Sakharov with American scholars J. Stone and F. von Hippel(?), with cover letter to M. Gorbachev from V. Chebrikov, 1987 February(?) (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 114)
    - Memorandum to M. Gorbachev from V. Chebrikov, Chairman of the KGB, re additional measures to strengthen security of the Party and government leaders, 1987 March (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 115)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS re amendments to Articles 70 and 190' of the Criminal Code of the RSFSR, 1987 May (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 116)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from A. Rekunkov and F. Bobkov re investigation of the criminal case of the German pilot M. Rust [who landed near Red Square in Moscow], 1987 July (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 117)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Chebrikov, A. Kovalev,IU. Skliarov, and V. Zagladin re an appeal of L. Peltier, citizen of the United States, for political asylum in the USSR; draft resolution of the TsK KPSS; instructions to the Soviet ambassador to the United States, 1987 August (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 118)
    - File is unavailable, 1918-1992 (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 119)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from E. Shevardnadze, L. Zaikov,V. Chebrikov, and A. N. Yakovlev re the intention of anti-social elements to hold a Seminar on Human Rights in Moscow; draft resolution of the TsK KPSS on measures to neutralize the activity of Glasnost (Free Speech) press club and to denounce human rights activists, 1987 December (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 120)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from L. Zaikov, V. Chebrikov,E. Shevardnadze, A. N. Yakovlev, A. Dobrynin, and A. Lukianov re measures to localize provocative actions of the participants in the Seminar on Human Rights; amendments to the memorandum from A. Dobrynin, 1987 December (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 121)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Kriuchkov and A. Sukharev re additional legal regulations for the activity of organs and troops of the Committee for State Security (KGB); draft resolution of the TsK KPSS, with the voting record of Politburo members; draft decree of the Presidium of the USSR Supreme Soviet; notes from A. Lukianov (handwritten) and V. Zhizhin re the decree, 1989 April-May (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 122)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from L. Zaikov, E. Shevardnadze, D. Yazov, O. Baklanov, I. Belousov, V. Kriuchkov, and K. Katushev re supply of the 9K52 (Moon-M) tactical missile complex to Afghanistan; draft resolution of the TsK KPSS, 1989 July (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 123)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Kriuchkov, Chairman of the KGB, re the intention of anti-social elements to hold a KGB and Perestroĭka international conference in Moscow; several notes of top party officials (including one by M. Gorbachev), 1989 July (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 124)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Kriuchkov re transfer of state-owned country houses (dachas) from assets of the Committee for State Security (KGB) to the Ministry of Health; draft resolution of the TsK KPSS; joint draft resolution of the TsK KPSS and the USSR Council of Ministers, 1989 July-August (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 125)
    - File is unavailable, 1918-1992 (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 126)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Kriuchkov, Chairman of the KGB, re establishing a Directorate for Defense of the Soviet Regime under the Committee for State Security (KGB), 1989 August (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 127)
    - File is unavailable, 1918-1992 (Opis 18, Reel 1.994, File 128)
  - Opis 19
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from A. Gromyko, Minister of Foreign Affairs, re policy of the Soviet delegation to the 21st Session of the UN Human Rights Commission; draft resolution of the TsK KPSS; draft directives to the delegations from the USSR and Ukraine at the 21st Session, 1965 February-March (Opis 19, Reel 1.995, File 1)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from A. Gromyko and R. Rudenko summarizing provisions of the Convention on Civil and Political Rights and of the Convention on Economic, Social, and Cultural Rights, adopted at the 21st Session of the UN General Assembly, and Soviet policy toward the conventions; draft resolution of the TsK KPSS; draft resolution of the USSR Council of Ministers, 1966 December - 1967 January (Opis 19, Reel 1.995, File 2)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from A. Gromyko re policy of the Soviet delegation to the International Conference on Human Rights in Teheran (1968); draft resolution of the TsK KPSS; draft letter to the Chairman of the International Conference on Human Rights from A. Kosygin, Chairman of the USSR Council of Ministers; draft directives to the Soviet delegation to the Conference; directives to the Soviet ambassadors to Hungary, the German Democratic Republic, Yugoslavia, Romania, Poland, Cuba, Czechoslovakia, Bulgaria, and Mongolia, 1968 March-April (Opis 19, Reel 1.995, File 3)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from A. Gromyko re policy of the Soviet delegation to the annual UN seminar On Liberty of Association (1968: London); draft resolution of the TsK KPSS; draft directives to the Soviet representative at the seminar, 1968 May-June (Opis 19, Reel 1.995, File 4)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Kuznetsov re policy of the Soviet delegation to the 25th Session of the UN Human Rights Commission; draft resolution of the TsK KPSS; draft directives to the Soviet delegation to the Session, 1969 January (Opis 19, Reel 1.995, File 5)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Kuznetsov re policy of the Soviet delegation to the UN International Seminar On Human Rights in Developing Countries in Nicosia (Cyprus); draft resolution of the TsK KPSS; draft directives to the Soviet delegation to the seminar, 1969 May-June (Opis 19, Reel 1.995, File 6)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Kuznetsov re policy of the Soviet delegation to the 30th Session of the UN Human Rights Commission in New York; draft resolution of the TsK KPSS; draft directives to the Soviet delegation to the Session, 1974 January (Opis 19, Reel 1.995, File 7)
    - Memorandum to the TsK KPSS from V. Kuznetsov re policy of the Soviet delegation to the 31st Session of the UN Human Rights Commission in Geneva; draft resolution of the TsK KPSS; draft directives to the Soviet delegation to the Session, 1975 January (Opis 19, Reel 1.995, File 8)